{"tossups": [{"question": "Felix Manz [mahnz] became the first martyr of this movement when he was drowned by the government of Zurich. Members of the Batenburger sect of this movement unusually embraced violence while spreading the faith. In 1534, a communal society created by this religious sect was forcibly suppressed in Munster. The Mennonites and the Amish are both direct descendants of this sect. For 10 points, name this Protestant movement whose name derives from its belief that believers should only be baptized as adults.", "answer": "<b><u>Anabaptism</u></b> [or <b><u>Anabaptists</u></b>; accept <b><u>Swiss Brethren</u> </b>before Batenburger sect] [Blake N<u>eff]</u>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This ruler employed a physician who combated rampant paranoia about the undead in Moravia and worked with the Count von Haugwitz to reform the empire. This employer of Gerard von Swieten was consort to the Duke of Lorraine, Francis Stephen, and signed the Treaty of Breslau to end the First Silesian War. The Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle [ex-luh-shuh-pell] ended a war begun after this ruler's ascension, in violation of Salic Law, under the Pragmatic Sanction. For 10 points, name this Habsburg Queen who fought the War of the Austrian Succession.", "answer": "<b><u>Maria Theresa</u></b> Walburga Amalia Christina  [Chris Ray]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s absent mother was included in a procession in an 1807 painting of an event involving him. This man touches a plague victim during a visit to Jaffa in a Jean-Antoine Gros [grow] painting, and Charlemagne and Hannibal\u2019s names appear in rock in another painting of him. He crowns his wife in a depiction of his own coronation. In another portrait, he rides a rearing horse and points into the air. For 10 points, name this French emperor shown crossing the Alps in a painting by Jacques-Louis David [dah-veed].", "answer": "<b><u>Napoleon</u><u>Bonaparte</u></b> [accept either underlined part; or <b><u>Napoleon I</u></b>] [Aseem Ke<u>yal]</u>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Phil Ochs\u2019 [oaks] song \u201cOutside of a Small Circle of Friends\u201d was inspired by this person\u2019s fate. Social scientists have used this person\u2019s story as an example of the diffusion of  responsibility and the bystander effect. After this Queens resident was stabbed by Winston Moseley, she was the subject of the New York Times article \u201cThirty-Seven Who Saw Murder Didn\u2019t Call the Police.\u201d For 10 points, name this New York City resident who was murdered in plain view of many unhelpful witnesses.", "answer": "Kitty <b><u>Genovese</u></b> [or Catherine Susan <b><u>Genovese</u></b>]  [Evan Adams]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This party controlled government during the Thirteen Wasted Years. It lost power in 1974 with the failure of leader Edward Heath, but regained it when its opponents suffered the \u201cWinter  of Discontent.\u201d In the 1980s, this party dealt with a miners\u2019 strike in its efforts to weaken unions and privatize state industries. For 10 points, name this British political party once led by Margaret Thatcher, which opposes the Labour Party.", "answer": "<b><u>Conservative</u></b> Party [or the <b><u>Conservatives</u></b>; or the <b><u>Tories</u></b>] [Matt Bollin<u>ger]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This region\u2019s Qajar [kah-JAR] Dynasty was founded by a eunuch. Another of its rulers invaded India and carried away the Peacock Throne. This nation was led by Nadir. Another leader of this nation signed a deal with the company that would become BP to develop this region\u2019s oil fields. That ruler belonged to the Pahlavi [pah-lah-vee] Dynasty. For 10 points, name this country that, before the Islamic Revolution, was ruled by the Shah.", "answer": "<b><u>Persia</u></b> [or <b><u>Iran</u></b>]  [Bruce Arth<u>ur]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man's most famous campaign led to the death of Margaret Whitehead, and he was captured by Benjamin Phipps. He alleged that he saw hieroglyphics on stalks of corn before his most famous action. Thomas R. Gray compiled the \u201cconfessions\u201d of this man, who was hanged after being captured in the Great Dismal Swamp. For 10 points, name this man who led an 1831 slave rebellion in Southampton County, Virginia.", "answer": "Nat <b><u>Turner</u> </b> [Abid Haseeb]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An obelisk stands at the death site of this group\u2019s member Charles Floyd, one of the \u201cnine young men from Kentucky.\u201d Toussaint Charbonneau was hired to serve as a translator for this group. This group, which included a dog named Seaman and a slave named York, wintered at Fort Mandan. For 10 points, name this group also known as the Corps of Discovery, which was dispatched by Thomas Jefferson to explore the newly purchased Louisiana Territory.", "answer": "the <b><u>Lewis and Clark</u></b> expedition [or <b><u>Corps of Discovery</u></b> until mentioned] [Evan Adams]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One type of this food relies on a terrain known as the dehesa [day-hay-suh], where acorns from holm oak and cork trees provide the distinctive taste of the iberico bellota variety. Cato the Elder described making it by first removing the ankle joint, then salting and smoking. A variety associated with Parma is dry-cured and aged for up to two years. Types popular in the U.S.  include Smithfield ones from Virginia, as well as hickory-smoked and honey-cured. For 10 points, name this cured meat product made from the hind leg of a pig.", "answer": "<b><u>ham</u></b> [or <b><u>jamon</u></b>; prompt on answers describing (the leg of a) <b><u>pig</u></b> until mentioned; prompt on \u201c<b><u>pork</u></b>\u201d]  [Dennis Loo<u>]</u>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A letter written by this man praises Walter Pater's <em>Marius the Epicurean</em> and asserts,\"Christ's place indeed is with the poets.\" This man was imprisoned after suing the Marquess of  Queensberry for libel, after which he wrote \"The Ballad of Reading Gaol [jail].\" In his most famous play, a character discovered in a handbag in a Victoria Station attempts to win the hand of Gwendolen Fairfax. For 10 points, name this author of <em>The Importance of Being Earnest</em> and <em>The Picture of Dorian Gray</em>.", "answer": "Oscar <b><u>Wilde</u></b> [or Oscar Fingal O'Flahertie Wills <b><u>Wilde</u></b>] [Chris Manners]", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This team won a match referred to by their opponents as the \u201crobbery of the century\u201d because Antonio Rattin was sent off. A shot that hit the crossbar and bounced onto the goal line gave this team its only World Cup victory, over West Germany in 1966. In 1950, this team suffered a shocking World Cup loss to the United States. For 10 points, name this national soccer team that plays home games at Wembley Stadium in London.", "answer": "<b><u>England</u></b> [or the <b><u>English</u></b> national team; or the <b><u>Three Lions</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on <b><u>Scotland</u></b><u>,</u> <b><u>Wales</u></b><u>,</u> <b><u>Northe</u><u>rn Irela</u><u>nd</u></b>, <b><u>Great Britain</u></b>, o<u>r</u> <b><u>United Kin</u><u>gdom</u></b>]  BO<u>NUS: En</u>g<u>land w</u>a<u>s eliminated from</u> th<u>e 2014 World</u> Cup<u> after a 2-1 group</u> stage loss to this team, which both won and hosted the first World Cup in 1930. ANSWER: <b><u>Uruguay</u></b> [or the <b><u>Uruguayan</u></b> national team; or La <b><u>Celeste</u></b>; or <b><u>Charruas</u></b>] [Rob Carso<u>n]</u>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This event was discovered by Frank Wills, after being approved by Jeb Magruder. Elliot Richardson resigned rather than fire Archibald Cox, a special prosecutor investigating this event. H.R. Haldeman was imprisoned for his role in this event, which was organized by the Committee to Re-Elect the President. For 10 points, name this scandal in which a hotel break-in led to the resignation of Richard Nixon.", "answer": "<b><u>Watergate</u></b> break-in [or equivalents such as <b><u>Watergate</u></b> scandal, prompt on  \u201cSaturday Night Massacre\u201d]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One politician from this country, Rena Dourou [door-ooh], was recently attacked on national television. A January 2015 election here saw the center-right New Democracy lose power to the left-wing Syriza [sur-ree-zuh] party, which ran on an anti-austerity platform. Its finance minister recently secured a four-month bailout extension from the \u201ctroika.\u201d [troy-kuh] For 10 points, Alexis Tsipras [sip-priss] leads what indebted Eurozone country, whose capital is Athens?", "answer": "<b><u>Greece</u> </b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This man led a parade of 50,000 through the streets of New York City after a 1920  international convention at Liberty Hall. He was indicted for mail fraud in connection with the Black Star Line, a shipping line he created under the Universal Negro Improvement Association. For 10 points, name this Jamaican political leader who promoted Pan-Africanism and a return to Africa.", "answer": "Marcus Mosiah <b><u>Garvey</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This author wrote of a colonel serving Queen Anne in <em>The History of Henry Esmond</em> and of an  Irishman who fights in the Seven Years\u2019 War and the American Revolution in <em>The Luck of Barry</em> <em>Lyndon</em>. Another of his novels opens at Miss Pinkerton\u2019s Academy and contrasts the  manipulative Becky Sharp with the na\u00efve Amelia Sedley. For 10 points, name this Victorian author of <em>Vanity Fair</em>.", "answer": "William Makepeace <b><u>Thackeray</u> </b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "This city contained an internal, artificial harbor created for military use called a <em>cothon</em> [koh-thahn]. Its citadel, the <em>byrsa</em> [bursa], was supposedly surrounded with strips of oxhide by its founder. This city was supplanted in its region by Utica until it was re-founded by Julius Caesar,  nearly a century after salt was supposedly sown in its soils following Cato the Elder\u2019s call for its destruction. For 10 points, name this rival of Rome during the Punic Wars.", "answer": "<b><u>Carthage</u></b> [or <b><u>Carthago</u></b>; or <b><u>Qart-Hadasht</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "An early battle in this conflict was the clash at Covadonga, which was a victory for the Visigoth Pelayo. Its turning point is usually considered the defeat of the Almohads at the 13th century Battle of Las Navas de Tolosa. The union of several factions in this conflict led to the joint rule of the Dual Monarchs. El Cid was a heroic figure from, for 10 points, what conflict concluded by Ferdinand and Isabella that ended the period of Islamic government in Spain?", "answer": "<b><u>Reconquista</u></b> of Iberia [or the <b><u>reconquest</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This woman aided Richard Harman, who was arrested for smuggling illegal Tyndale Bibles.  This woman\u2019s influence is credited with causing the downfall of Lord Chancellor Thomas Wolsey. Along with musician Mark Smeaton, this niece of Thomas Howard was imprisoned in the Tower of London on charges of adultery. For 10 points, name this woman executed in 1536, the second wife of Henry VIII.", "answer": "Anne <b><u>Boleyn</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Ancient gods worshiped by this ethnic group included Uzza [ooz-ah] and Hubal. It</u></b>  <b><u>fought the Byzantine Empire at the Battle of Yarmouk. This ethnic group\u2019s rebellion was</u></b> <b><u>subdued in the Wars of Apostasy, after which their invasions brought down the</u><u> (+)</u> <u>Sassanid [sass-uh-nihd] Empire. This ethnic group loyally followed the Rashidu</u>n [rash-ee-done] after being subdued by (*)</b> Abu Bakr [ah-boo bah-kur], and originally pledged loyalty to a prophet who took dictation from Gabriel in a cave. For 10 points, name this largely Islamic ethnic group that populates a peninsula northeast of Africa.", "answer": "<b><u>Arab</u></b>s [do not accept or prompt on \u201cMuslims\u201d]  [Matt Bollin<u>ger]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Regina Ip resigned from the government of Tung Chee-hwa in this city after 2003\u2019s 1</u></b> <b><u>Ju</u><u>ly March. That march was in protest of Article 23 of this city\u2019s</u><u> (+) Basic Law. The \u201cr</u>ight <u>of abode\u201d in this city was expanded by its Court of Final Appeal i</u>n 1999</b>.<b> This city was the site of (*)</b> 2014 protests aimed at the ouster of Chief Executive CY Leung that were termed the \u201cUmbrella Revolution.\u201d The United Kingdom returned this city to its present country in 1997 after a 99-year lease. For 10 points, name this city, a Special Administrative Region of China.", "answer": "<b><u>Hong Kong</u></b> Special Administrative Region [or <b><u>HKSAR</u></b>; or <b><u>Xianggang</u></b>] [Mark Arild<u>sen]</u>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>Two years before this scandal, a group central to it was involved in Operation Tipped</u></b> <b><u>Ke</u><u>ttle. In one part of this scandal, Israeli shipments of BGM-71 anti-tank</u><u> (+) missiles w</u>ere <u>supposed to achieve the release of American hostages. This scandal was p</u>artly the result of the Boland Amendment, which limited funding for opponents of the (*)</b> Sandinista [sand-duh-nees-tuh] National Liberation Front. For 10 points, name this mid-1980s scandal that resulted in the indictments of Oliver North and Caspar Weinberger, in which weapons were sold to a Middle Eastern country in order to fund anti-communist rebels in Nicaragua.", "answer": "<b><u>Iran-Contra</u></b> affair [or <b><u>Irangate</u></b>; or <b><u>Contragate</u></b>; accept scandal in place of affair] [Dennis Lo<u>o]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In a novel by this author, Edgar, the Master of Ravenswood, dies in quicksand after</u></b> <b><u>Lu</u><u>cy stabs Bucklaw in a bridal chamber. This author of</u> </b><em><b><u>The Bride of Lammermoor</u></b></em><b><u> wr</u><u>ote a</u></b> <b><u>novel in which</u><u> (+) El Desdichado [dess-dee-cod-oh] jousts with Maurice de Bracy and other</u></b> <b>knights. Frank Osbaldistone narrates this author\u2019s novel (*)</b><em>Rob Roy,</em> which is part of his <em>Waverley</em> series. Cedric the Saxon\u2019s son, Wilfrid, is the title character of this author\u2019s novel set in 12th-century England. For 10 points, name this British author of historical romances such as <em>Ivanhoe</em>.", "answer": "Sir Walter <b><u>Scott</u> </b> [Ike Jose]", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b><u>This problem was first described by RAND Corporation members Merrill Flood and</u></b> <b><u>M</u><u>elvin Dresher, and it was formalized by Albert W. Tucker. A computer tournament</u></b> <b><u>involving this problem was won by a four-line program written by Anatol</u><u> (+) Rapapo</u>rt <u>named \u201cTit-for-Tat,\u201d as described in Robert Axelrod\u2019s book</u> </b><em><b><u>The Evolutio</u></b><b>n of </b></em><b>(*) </b><em>Cooperation</em>. A variation of its iterated version is called the \u201cpeace-war game\u201d. For 10 points, name this scenario from game theory in which two criminals in separate jail cells are given the choice of remaining silent or betraying their partner.", "answer": "the <b><u>prisoner\u2019s dilemma</u> </b> [Dennis Loo, ed<u>. Rob Carson]</u>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "<b><u>The state of Cundinamarca [koon-deen-uh-mark-uh] was set up in this modern-day</u></b> <b><u>co</u><u>untry, whose capital was recaptured at the end of the \u201cFoolish Fatherland\u201d period.</u></b> <b><u>Periods of unrest in this country have included the War of the Thousand Days and th</u><u>e mid-</u><u>20th-century struggle called \u201cLa</u> <u>(+) Violencia.\u201d This country</u> </b><em><b><u>lost</u></b></em><b><u> western territory when</u> <u>Philippe Jean Bunau-Varilla help</u>ed orchestrate a 1903 revolution against it that promoted (*) </b>canal-building interests. For 10 points, identify this country from which Panama gained independence.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Colombia</u> </b> [Will Alston - ed. Jeff H<u>oppes]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One ruler from this kingdom led the \u201cLong campaign\u201d and was captured following a</u></b> <b><u>de</u><u>feat at the battle of Varna. The Black Army led by the son of that ruler successfully</u></b> <b><u>besieged Vienna and engaged in many conflicts with the Ottomans. Besides</u><u> (+) Janos</u> <u>Hunyadi [hoon-yah-dee] and Matthias Corvinus [kore-vine-us], other leade</u>rs from the Arpad dynasty here include its founder, (*) </b>Stephen I. The Treaty of Trianon formally abolished this kingdom, whose privileges were confirmed by the Ausgleich [oss-glike] of 1867.  For 10 points, name this Magyar kingdom later absorbed into a dual-monarchy with Austria.", "answer": "<b><u>Hungary</u> </b> [Zihan Zhen<u>g]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A formative moment for this man was the murder of his mentor Cornstalk. This man</u></b>  <b><u>ridiculed the notion of selling land, saying \u201cSell a country! Why not sell the air?\u201d He</u></b>  <b><u>refused to recognize the Treaty of</u> (+) Greenville, and decried the \u201cpeace chiefs\u201d who had <u>signed it. Richard Mentor Johnso</u>n claimed to have killed this man, whose brother Tenskwatawa was known as \u201cthe Prophet.\u201d After his death at the Battle of the (*)</b> Thames, his Native American confederation broke up. For 10 points, name this Shawnee chief who allied with the British during the War of 1812.", "answer": "<b><u>Tecumseh</u></b> [or <b><u>Tecumtha</u></b>; or <b><u>Tikamthe</u></b>]  [Saul Hanki<u>n]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}